"Does Coffee Help Boost
Autophagy and Lifespan?"
When food is scarce, our body
detects this lack of nutrients
and shifts
into conservation mode,
turning up the process
of autophagy,
from the Greek "auto"
meaning "self"
and "phagy" meaning "to eat."
Autophagy means,
quite literally,
eating yourself.
Autophagy plays
two major roles:
nutrient recovery
(breakdown products
re-entering cellular metabolism)
and quality control
(the removal of superfluous,
damaged,
or dangerous components).
In the modern context
of not just sufficient food,
but an excess of it,
our baseline rate of autophagy
is low
and slips down even further
as we get older.
A decline in autophagic capacity
with age has been described
in almost all animals analyzed,
including humans.
Autophagy appears to not only
be necessary for life extension,
but, also, in some cases,
sufficient for
increasing longevity.
Boosting autophagy alone
can lengthen lifespan in mice
by an average of 17 percent,
as well as improve
their healthspan.
No wonder autophagy
is at the forefront
of so much longevity research.
The most reliable way to kick
autophagy into high gear
may be to eat less food
altogether,
but there is a downside
to caloric restriction.
Starving yourself, as was
understated in a major review,
"generates discomfort."
There is, however,
something we can consume
that induces autophagy
that many people
find comforting: coffee.
We've long known
that alcohol consumption
causes liver inflammation,
but an unexpected finding
was made by a group
of Norwegian researchers
back in 1986:
Coffee consumption was associated
with less liver inflammation.
Subsequent studies
conducted around the world
replicated these results.
In the United States,
for example,
those at risk for liver disease
who drank more than two cups
(475 ml) of coffee a day
appeared to have
less than half the risk
of developing
chronic liver disease
as those who drank less
than one cup.
The fact that regular coffee
consumption seems protective
against the development
of fatty liver disease
gave researchers an idea.
Since autophagy plays
such an important role
in clearing fat
out of the liver,
the researchers tested
to see whether caffeine
might have
cell-cleansing properties.
Indeed, it was found to be
a potent autophagy stimulant.
So, does coffee or caffeine
extend the lifespan
of model organisms
like yeast and worms?
Yes...
and yes.
In mice, coffee
rapidly triggered autophagy
within hours
at a human-equivalent dose,
and decaffeinated coffee
worked just as well.
The autophagy-promoting
properties of coffee
were independent
of the caffeine content.
Both regular and decaf
also had similar
anti-aging effects
on another aging pathway
in mice.
But what about in people?
A systematic review
of the health impacts of coffee
on liver diseases concluded
that "daily coffee consumption
should be encouraged"
in patients
with chronic liver disease.
But if coffee
enhances autophagy,
shouldn't its benefits extend
to a wide range of diseases?
Well, coffee intake
is also associated
with lower risk
of kidney disease,
along with reduced risk
of conditions
as varied as gout,
Parkinson's disease,
type 2 diabetes,
and skin cancer.
Decaf was also associated with a
range of potential health benefits.
The results are all
the more remarkable
given many of the studies may
have failed to adequately control
for smoking and
unhealthy food intake,
both of which tend to go
along with coffee drinking.
So, coffee drinkers
appeared to be healthier
even despite their tendency
for less wholesome habits.
Does all this translate
into living longer?
Apparently so.
We only have
observational research
on coffee and mortality
in humans,
but, to date, more than
20 studies around the world
following more than ten million
individuals over time
have found that those drinking
three cups (720 ml)
of coffee a day had 13 percent
lower risk of death.
If practiced
throughout adulthood,
that would be expected
to translate
into approximately
an extra year of life.
In terms of longevity,
three cups of decaf
appeared to be
just as protective
as three cups
of regular coffee,
so it's not the caffeine.
This is supported by data
showing the longevity link
regardless of whether people were
slow or fast metabolizers of caffeine.
If it's not the caffeine,
then what was it?
Coffee contains more than
a thousand bioactive compounds.
The polyphenol chlorogenic acid
is the most abundant antioxidant
in coffee beans,
so researchers started there
and found it was indeed
able to enhance autophagy
in cultured human cells.
So, which brands
and types of coffee
have the most of this
autophagy-boosting compound?
We'll find out next.